When a person has extreme social anxiety,
所謂的“交流障礙症” 是指不擅長和人交流的一種症狀
they struggle to communicate with others.
或是指有這種症狀的人
Bear in mind, they only struggle to form connections.
不過需要注意的是 這些人只是不擅長社交
It doesn't mean that they don't want to.
但並不表示他們不想和別人有往來
The story so far.
前情提要
Tadano's goal for high school is to help Komi make 100 friends.
只野同學訂下了高中生活的目標 就是幫古見同學交到100個朋友
MISSION 02 "IT'S JUST A CHILDHOOD FRIEND."
（任務02 是兒時玩伴）
My job will be easy.
所以我要做的事就很簡單
I'll approach my classmates saying…
只需要跟班上同學說一聲
Komi says she wants friends.
聽說古見同學很想交朋友喔
Wow! I'll be her friend!
哇！我要當她的朋友！
FLOAT…
（想像）
POP!
（回神）
I've visualized it, now I can do it!
已經做好情境想像訓練了！
So who…
所以該找誰搭話呢？
HA HA TEE-HEE
（嬉笑）
Oh!
啊！
The new frappe at Standbakes is super cute and yummy!
星七克新出的星繽樂 超可愛而且超好喝的！
Yamai, have you tried it?
-好！ -山井已經喝過了呀？
Of course! You gotta try it.
當然啊！我真的很推薦
-Let's go together! -Yeah!
-下次我們一起去吧！ -好！
Um, ah…
不好意思，那個…
Yamai?
山井同學
FREEZE
（靜止）
Huh? Yes, Tadano?
嗯？只野同學，什麼事？
Uh, um, actually, about Komi…
啊，是這樣的，古見同學她…
Could you…
想要交朋…
-Hee-hee. -Huh?
-嘻嘻 -什麼？
Huh? You dare speak the exalted one's name?
你是什麼東西？ 竟敢稱呼那位尊貴大小姐的名諱
It's "Her Majesty," trashbag.
你這沒用的男人，得叫“古見大人”
You just sit beside her. You're still trash.
不要以為你坐在 她隔壁就可以這麼囂張
You're worthless, yet breathe the same air.
比馬糞還要低賤的東西 能夠和古見大人呼吸一樣的空氣
Be grateful, trash. Trash, trash, trash…
就該感恩了，人渣…
Trash!
人渣！
And?
所以有什麼事？
Oh, uh, nothing.
不，沒事
Is that so? Okay, never talk to me again.
這樣啊，那你別再來跟我們說話了
Tadano was once again reminded of his social position.
只野同學再度確認了 自己在班上的地位
LUNCH TIME
（午休時間）
HE TRIED WITH SEVERAL OTHERS, ONLY TO GET THE SAME RESULT.
（後來只野同學又去找幾個人說話 但是都得到了一樣的反應）
I'm…
我…
friendless.
根本沒朋友
I told Komi I'd help her.
我說了要幫古見同學交朋友
But I can't if I don't have any friends.
但我自己都沒朋友，完全幫不上忙
How conceited of me to say I'd help.
我憑什麼那麼自負，還說要幫她
Sorry Komi.
古見同學，對不起
I'm…
我…
useless.
是個沒用的人
But there's still one thing I can do.
不過還是有能做的事！
I wanted to avoid doing this if at all possible…
雖然我實在不想去找那傢伙
But there's someone Komi could definitely be friends with.
但那傢伙應該 也可以和古見同學成為朋友
See ya later!
那待會見囉
Bye!
待會見
O-Osana…
長名同學…
Huh?
什麼？
Oh!
是你啊！
What's up all of a sudden?
幹嘛突然來找我？
Got business with your childhood friend, Najimi Osana?
你有事找我這個 兒時玩伴長名馴染嗎？
Tadano?
只野同學
And Komi.
和古見同學
Where did you come from?
妳也在這裡啊？
Uh, she's Najimi Osana.
我來介紹，她叫長名馴染
-We went to junior high together. -Yeah!
-是我國中的同班同學 -耶！
Huh? "She"?
等等，“她”？
Uh, you…
怎麼會…
Why are you wearing a skirt?
怎麼會穿著裙子啊？
What are you talking about, Tadano?
你在說什麼呀？只野同學
I'm a girl!
我是女生啊！
Of course I'm wearing a skirt!
穿裙子不是理所當然的事嗎？
-Or maybe it's Scottish tradi-- -No!
-還是你以為這是蘇格蘭民族服… -我不是指這個！
In junior high you always wore a boy's uniform.
國中時你明明是男生啊 你都穿著男生制服吧？
Huh? What? You've misunderstood!
有這回事嗎？你記錯了吧？
-Tadano! That's just like you. -No, I'm certain of it!
-真是的，你這人就是少根筋 -不！
Hee-hee.
嘿嘿
Najimi Osana is just like that.
長名馴染就是這樣的人
Uncertain gender.
性別不明
Says one thing and does another.
言行不一
Compulsive liar.
說謊成性
And above all…
最重要的是…
Najimi, did you see that TV show?
馴染，有看昨天那個嗎？
Oh, Draining the River?
喔，你是說《河水抽光好吃驚》嗎？
Najimi! Want to check out club activities with me?
馴染，要不要一起去參觀社團活動？
Oh, sorry. How about tomorrow?
抱歉，改明天可以嗎？
Okay!
知道了！
Na-Najimi. Here's the book I borrowed.
馴染，這是上次跟你借的小說
Oh, Jaysus right? How was it?
是《耶酥酥！》啊，好看嗎？
Hey Najimi, don't say the title in front of everyone.
不要在大庭廣眾前 說出輕小說書名啦！
Yeah… What's really impressive…
這令人驚異的…
are those people skills!
社交能力！
Oh, that was really fresh!
那還滿恐怖的！
KOMI'S SURPRISED.
（感到吃驚）
Osana. Are all these people…
長名同學，該不會這些人…
Huh? Yeah. My childhood friends.
什麼？是啊，他們都是我的兒時玩伴
I knew it.
又來了
I mean, all the students in the school are my childhood friends.
不如說全校同學都是我的兒時玩伴
VERY SURPRISED.
（非常吃驚）
That's how it was in junior high too.
從國中時就是這樣
Over half the students were childhood friends of Osana's.
學校過半數學生 都是長名馴染的兒時玩伴
I heard it was because of family circumstances.
他本人說是因為父母工作常調派各地
But that's not it.
但重點不在這裡
What's unusual are those people skills.
不尋常的是他那社交能力
Making friends in minutes.
可以和任何人在 兩到三分鐘內成為朋友
And such a strong personality, unforgettable after a single meeting.
一旦成了朋友 任誰都忘不了他那獨特的個性
It's a special power.
這根本就是一種特殊能力
But that's exactly why…
但正因為他是這樣的人…
-See ya. -Bye.
-下次見 -拜拜
Osana. I need a favor.
長名同學，我有事想拜託你
A favor for my old buddy? Ask away.
好，摯友拜託我的 任何事我一定做到
-Can my body satisfy your carnal desires? -Stop it, Komi's here.
-要用我的肉體發洩你過剩的精力？ -不要再說了，古見同學也在這裡
Uh.
喔
That's a joke.
他是開玩笑的啦
Um.
不好意思
This is who we're dealing with, but Osana's not a bad person… I think…
他雖然是這種個性，但應該不是壞人
If you're up for it, the phrase we practiced this morning…
如果妳不介意 或許可以把早上練習過的那句話…
Ah, she doesn't get it.
看來她是沒聽懂
"Let's be friends."
“請跟我做朋友”
L…
請…
You're doing better than this morning!
比早上進步了！
What's going on? What is this?
什麼？這是在搞什麼？
She's saying, "Let's be friends."
她在說“請跟我做朋友”
MAYBE…
（應該是啦…）
Really? Really??
真的嗎？你是說真的嗎？
That was the favor.
我要拜託你的就是這件事
Would you be Komi's friend?
可以請你跟古見同學做朋友嗎？
It'll be easy for you, right?
對你來說應該很容易吧？
Oh, uh, I see.
好，我懂了
Sorry. That's uh…
抱歉，可是這件事…
Not… possible.
有點困難
FROZEN FROM SHOCK
（受到打擊而僵住）
Komi? Komi!
古見同學？古見同學！
Osana. Get over here.
長名同學，過來一下
Okay!
好！
What are you thinking? Why did you turn her down?
你在想什麼啊？為什麼要拒絕啊？
You're the national champ of people skills!
你的社交能力不是全國第一嗎？
I wouldn't say national champ.
不，說不上是全國第一
Hey, I'm sorry.
哎呀，抱歉啦
I'm just not into Komi.
其實我不擅長跟古見同學相處
Huh?
什麼？
Is there such a person?
居然會有你不擅長相處的人類？
Who do you think she is?
你把古見同學當成什麼了？
I told you. I'm a childhood friend of everyone here.
我剛才不是說了嗎？ 全校學生都是我的兒時玩伴
I've met Komi before.
我以前也見過古見同學
Oh.
哦
We were in second grade.
那是我國小二年級的事
Komi!
古見同學！
You're going home?
妳要回去了嗎？
Let's play a bit!
陪我玩嘛！
Hey Komi.
好不好？古見同學！
K-Komi?
古見同學？
Hey…
喂
No matter what I said, she ignored me.
無論我說什麼，她都不理我
Komi's the only person I couldn't befriend.
她是我唯一無法變要好的人
I was in bed for a week from the shock.
害我大受打擊，臥床一個禮拜
So Komi has always been Komi.
原來古見同學從小就是那樣啊
I'm a mature person, so I won't say I hate her.
我是個成熟的大人了 所以我不會說我討厭古見同學
But when our eyes meet,
但是一和她對上眼…
I get chills.
我就會發抖
Oh… I see.
這樣啊
But you've misunderstood.
但是你誤會了
Komi didn't ignore you. Just talk to her and you'll understand.
古見同學她不是不理你 你去跟她說話就知道了
I know!
對了！
Could you walk home together? With Komi.
今天放學你可以跟她一起走嗎？
You're really aggressive, Tadano!
你很積極嘛，只野同學
But I've already done what I can.
可是我已經付出足夠的努力了
And it didn't work.
但卻徒勞無功
That's all.
這就說明了一切
Anyway, she's so popular.
況且她不是很受歡迎嗎？
She must have tons…
要交多少朋友都…
Oh.
啊
Just talk to her.
你去跟她說話就知道了
What's this? You're really pushing this Komi thing.
你幹嘛一直幫古見同學說話啊？
-You like her? -Huh?
-你是不是喜歡她啊？ -什麼？
No way. She's out of my league.
沒有啦，我哪配得上她啊
It's just…
只是…
Komi needed help, so I just wanted to…
看到她在苦惱，我就想幫幫她
Is that weird?
我這樣講很奇怪嗎？
OR TOO MEDDLESOME…?
（會不會太沉重了？）
Huh? No.
嗯？不會啊
I just thought you're pretty cool.
讓我覺得你果然很帥呢
-Makes me wet. -Where?
-害我濕了 -哪裡濕了？
Alright.
好啊
I'll walk home with Komi.
我找古見同學一起回去
Osana.
長名同學
-On one condition. -Oh.
-但是我有一個條件 -哦
Stop calling me Osana.
你不要再叫我長名同學了
We're old friends, right?
我們可是老朋友啊
Call me Najimi like you used to.
你就跟以前一樣叫我馴染吧
Remember those days?
真令人懷念
You wanted to ask that girl out.
你為了對喜歡的女生告白
So I helped you write "LOVE" on the field.
我曾幫你在操場寫下“愛”
Stop that!
不要說了，不要再提這件事了！
She really let you down hard.
天啊，想到你被甩的樣子…
Childhood friends know your shameful past.
兒時玩伴知道以前的黑歷史
Heh.
嘻嘻
That's why I didn't want to resort to this.
所以我才不想找這傢伙！
AFTER SCHOOL
（放學後）
MISSION 03 "I'M NOT A KILLER."
（任務03 不是殺手）
Want to walk home, Komi?
古見同學，那我們回去吧
So awkward…
感覺好尷尬
WALKING HOME NAJIMI CAM
（放學路上 馴染視角）
Sorry about before.
剛才很抱歉
Saying I can't be your friend.
我不該說和妳交朋友會有困難
I didn't mean it.
那不是我的真心話
Oh yeah!
對了！
You and I, we met before. Do you remember?
妳記得我們以前見過面嗎？
-…S! -STARTLE!
-…得 -“嚇”
Um… anyway.
話說回來…
You're v-very popular.
古見同學很受歡迎呢
What's your secret?
有沒有什麼祕訣啊？
RUMBLE
（隆隆聲）
TREMBLE
（顫抖）
Are you alright?
“還好嗎？”
WALKING HOME TADANO CAM
（放學路上 只野視角）
Sorry about before.
剛才很抱歉
Saying I can't be your friend.
我不該說和妳交朋友會有困難
I didn't mean it.
那不是我的真心話
TOO NERVOUS TO LOOK
（緊張得不敢看對方）
Oh yeah!
對了！
You and I, we met before. Do you remember?
妳記得我們以前見過面嗎？
SHE DIDN'T PRONOUNCE THE "YE," JUST THE "S."
（因為發不出聲音，“記”模糊不清 “得”聽起來很大聲）
Um… anyway.
話說回來…
You're v-very popular.
古見同學很受歡迎呢
What's your secret?
有沒有什麼祕訣啊？
REALLY WANTS TO DENY IT
（拼命想要否定）
Are you alright?
“還好嗎？”
I GIVE UP
（我放棄）
Not even Najimi can talk to her.
連馴染都沒辦法跟她對話啊
Najimi!
馴染！
Heh heh.
嘿嘿
I found you, Najimi.
馴染，終於找到你了
-Heh. -Oh!
-嘿 -哦
It's Maa and Shii!
這不是阿正和小強嗎？
What are you doing here?
你們怎麼跑來了？
You just moved away without saying anything!
誰叫你不說一聲就搬家！
Maa misses you, Najimi!
阿正很寂寞呢，馴染！
They're Najimi's friends! That was unexpected.
原來是馴染的兒時玩伴啊，嚇死我了
Yeah?
所以呢？
What's up?
找我有什麼事嗎？
Oh yeah.
對了
Yeah!
嗯！
Listen.
我啊
I realized this after you left.
在你離開後才發現
You mean so much to me.
你對我有多麼重要
Maa, you can do it!
阿正，加油！
Najimi.
馴染
Please go out with me!
請和我交往吧！
No. Anyway I'm a dude.
不要，而且我是男的
That was fast.
好快就拒絕了
WHICH ARE YOU…
（到底是男生還是女生啊？）
-Najimi. -Yeah?
-馴染 -幹嘛？
I've made up my mind.
我已經下定決心了
Huh?
什麼？
I'm going to trust my heart!
我要珍惜心中這份心動的感覺！
-Maa! -He's in deep…
-阿正！ -你是少女啊？
HEH HEH HEH
（奸笑）
SHOULD I HELP…?
（該去幫他嗎？）
Ow! Let me go!
好痛！放開我！
I won't let you get away again.
馴染，我不會再讓你逃走了
Huh?
什麼？
RUMBLE
（隆隆聲）
What's this pressure I'm feeling?
這股壓力是怎麼回事？
Huh?
什麼？
Oh, a chick. She's hot, too!
什麼嘛，居然是個女的 而且還是美女
What is it?
妳想幹嘛？
Huh? My house key?
什麼？我家的鑰匙？
I…
這…
key… you…
掉了…
Guurgh!
天啊！
She just said, "I'll kill you." Didn't she?
剛剛這女的是不是說“殺掉了”？
What's going on?
她這是什麼意思？
S-Surely not…
難道說…
Last time someone did that to Najimi I killed him!
“上次對馴染這麼做的人 已經被我殺掉了！
With his own house key!
就用那小子老家的鑰匙！”
That's what she's saying!
她是這個意思嗎？
Eek!
哇！
STARE
（瞪）
-L-Let's go, Shii! -Maa! Wait up!
-我們走，小強！ -什麼？阿正？
SHE WAS TRYING TO SAY, "I FOUND THIS KEY OF YOURS."
（她是想說“你的這個鑰匙掉了”）
Uh.
呃
It's alright, Komi!
古見同學，沒事的！
I think they just misunderstood.
他們應該是誤會了
I'll be your friend, Komi.
我可以和古見同學做朋友喔
Whoa.
喔
Uh.
呃
Hah!
噗！
Komi, you're hilarious.
古見同學，妳原來這麼有趣啊！
I had you all wrong.
原來我以前都誤會了！
Let's go.
我們一起回家吧
You made your second friend.
妳交到第2個朋友了呢
Huh?
什麼？
What should we do with this?
這該怎麼辦？
KEY
（鑰匙）
They took it to the police.
最後送去了派出所
She spoke to a stranger!
她對陌生人說話了耶！
Komi, you're growing up!
古見同學成長了！
MISSION 04 "IT'S JUST MY FIRST ERRAND."
（任務04 是首次替人跑腿）
LUNCH TIME
（午休時間）
Hey, Komi!
嗨，古見同學！
Do you want to eat lunch together?
要不要一起吃午飯？
NAJIMI FULL OF FEAR KOMI FULL OF JOY
（看到古見的眼睛會發抖 首次受邀共餐而感動）
They still have a long way to go.
原來還沒克服啊
Huh?
什麼？
Oh, it's you, Tadano.
在那裡的不是只野同學嗎？
Are you eating alone?
難道你一個人吃飯嗎？
GULP!
（驚）
Did you know?
你知道嗎？
Food tastes better if you eat with someone!
吃飯要和別人一起吃才好吃喔
I eat with my friends.
我都會和朋友一起吃
What about you?
怪了，那你呢？
Must I do everything for you?
你真的很讓人費心耶
If you insist, you can eat with us.
如果你堅持的話 讓你加入也是可以的啦
SLIGHTLY HAPPY
（有點開心）
What are you thinking?
只野同學，你在想什麼？
Eating with Her Majesty? Of course you can't.
你哪有資格和古見大人共餐
Her Majesty's lunch is sacred.
古見大人的用餐時間是神聖的
-Being in her sight is unacceptable. -No thanks.
-像你這種凡夫俗子不能進入視野… -不，我還是算了
Anyway, Komi. Why did you want to be friends?
話說回來，古見同學 為什麼會想和我交朋友啊？
You want more friends?
妳還有其他想交的朋友嗎？
This cream went on sale yesterday.
這是昨天新上市的護手霜
What shampoo do you use?
妳都用什麼洗髮精啊？
What do you think of Tadano?
妳覺得只野同學這人怎麼樣？
That looks tasty!
那個看起來好好吃！
Did you make it?
是妳自己做的嗎？
Yesterday at the store…
我上次在超商…
What music do you like? I like…
妳喜歡什麼音樂？我的話…
TALK TALK TALK
（滔滔不絕）
INFORMATION OVERLOAD
（資訊量太大讓古見同學大腦超載）
Komi wants to make a hundred friends.
古見同學說她想交100個朋友
A hundred…
100個
That's all?
這麼一點夠嗎？
Don't say that!
這種話不該說出口啊！
Ah, alright.
這樣啊
What are you scheming?
他在打什麼歪主意吧？
Oh, Komi.
啊，古見同學
You know…
不知為何…
I feel a little thirsty.
我忽然覺得好渴
Get me a Standbakes non-fat milk pistachio
妳去星七克幫我買一杯 脫脂牛奶開心果奶油
deep mocha dip cream frappaccino,
濃摩卡加巧克力糖漿的中杯星繽樂
medium with chocolate sauce and extra whip.
還要額外加打發鮮奶油
If you don't, I won't be your friend.
如果沒有買來，我就不跟妳做朋友了
Wha?!
什麼？
STAGGER
（搖晃）
Komi, you're going?
古見同學，妳要去嗎？
See ya!
慢走啊！
Najimi! That's coercion!
馴染，你這已經算恐嚇了吧！
It's fine. It's nearby.
別擔心，很近的啦
That's not what I meant.
這不是重點！
Huh.
哼
I did it for her sake.
這是為了古見同學好
It hurts me more.
我自己也很心疼啊
Asking for a non-fat milk pistachio--
叫她去買脫脂牛奶開心果奶油…
You don't need to say it.
你不用再重複一遍
It's training for Komi.
這是為了訓練她
To talk to people.
讓她學習和人交談
I don't actually need the drink.
絕不是因為我想喝飲料喔
You're clearly enjoying this.
可是你臉上帶著奸笑
What are you standing around for?
好了，你也別在這裡發呆了
You've got to follow her.
快去跟在古見同學後面
Just don't blow your cover.
當然不能被她發現喔
You're not coming?
你不一起來嗎？
I'm on a tight schedule.
別看我這樣，我可是很忙的
I've got three other lunch dates today.
今天午飯我還有其他三攤飯局
Who are you?
你到底是何方神聖啊？
STRANGER DANGER!!
（當心可疑人物！）
Oh.
喔
Here I am again.
我怎麼又扮演這種角色？
Mommy, a stalker!
媽媽，有跟蹤狂
Yes, a stalker.
是跟蹤狂呢
Huh?!
什麼？
LOITER
（徘徊）
Oh.
唉
COURAGE REQUIRED
（走進星七克需要勇氣）
AT LAST, KOMI GOES IN.
（古見同學下定決心走了進去）
KOMI GOES BACK OUT.
（古見同學暫時撤退）
She came back out.
她走出來了
KOMI TRIES AGAIN.
（古見同學再次努力鼓起勇氣）
Oh.
喔
Hello! What can I get you?
歡迎光臨，請問要點什麼？
TADANO HAS ENTERED.
（只野同學進來了）
Non-fat milk pistachio deep mocha dip cream frappaccino,
脫脂牛奶開心果奶油 濃摩卡加巧克力糖漿的中杯星繽樂
medium with chocolate sauce and extra whip.
還要額外加打發鮮奶油
GESTURE
（比手勢）
Um, here's the menu.
菜單在這邊
NOT THERE!
（沒有！）
CLOSE TO TEARS
（快哭了）
Look closely, Komi!
古見同學，再仔細找找看啊！
Miss?
小姐？
What will she do?
她要怎麼辦？
Ah!
啊！
I see it.
我知道了
I've worked at Standbakes for 15 years.
有15年資歷的我
I've earned an honor only given to those who pass the annual company exam.
唯有通過每年一次 公司內部考試才能獲得的稱號
One in twelve people.
每12人中只有1人合格
Only the chosen ones can wear this black apron.
脫穎而出的星七克店員 才能穿上這條黑色圍裙
Only a Coffee Master, a Dark Apron Barista like me can understand!
我是咖啡專家 黑圍裙咖啡師，所以我懂！
I know what this girl wants!
我知道這位少女想喝什麼！
Right away!
我知道了！
Please wait at the pick-up counter.
請到那邊取餐區稍候！
My amazing customer service will spread on Chwitter.
然後星七克店員 神對應的事蹟就會傳遍堆特
It'll get ten thousand rechweets for sure.
肯定會被轉發一萬次！
Your order of…
這是您點的…
-I DID GOOD. -WRONG.
（錯了，我做得真好）
KNOWS IT'S WRONG
（知道這杯是錯的）
WANTS TO TELL HIM
（想對店員說“錯了”）
I'll put it in a bag for you.
我來幫您裝到袋子
Thank you!
謝謝惠顧！
She left!
她就這麼回去了！
SHE COULDN'T SAY IT.
（但說不出口）
Oh, you're back Komi! No broken bones?
古見同學，妳回來了啊，沒受傷吧？
Oh!
哇！
Thanks, Komi! I've been looking forward…
謝謝妳，古見同學，我很期待…
to this.
喝這杯
Huh?
什麼？
-That's not it. -Ah.
-不是這杯 -啊
Huh?
天啊！
After that, they apologized profusely.
之後兩人拼命道歉
BONUS SCENE
（片尾彩蛋）
Hey.
天啊
I'm so sorry Komi. I didn't think it would come to this.
古見同學，很抱歉，我沒想到會這樣
STILL BOWING
（繼續低頭賠罪）
Hmph!
哼！
Komi's sulking. It's so cute!
古見同學在鬧彆扭，好可愛！
Subtitle translation by: Claire Tanaka
字幕翻譯：馬慈光